Elihu Thomson Papers 1865-1944 Mss.Ms.Coll.74
American Philosophical Society
- Series XII. Certificates, 1899-1937; 1 boxes; 0.5 linear feet
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers--Honorary membership certificate
  - American Welding Society--Honorary membership certificate
  - Belgian Kiddies, Ltd., 16 Mar. 1917
  - Boston Electric Club
  - Central High School of Philadelphia
  - Central High School of Philadelphia
  - Central High School of Philadelphia., 30 Dec. 1902
    Associated Alumni [certificate]
  - Central High School of Philadelphia.
    - Bachelor of Arts
  - Central High School of Philadelphia.
    - Constitution
  - Central High School of Philadelphia.
    - Master of Arts
  - Electrical Engineering Society
  - France Exposition. Grand Prix
  - France. National Order of the Legion of Honor
  - The Franklin Institute. The Elliot Cresson Gold Medal
  - The Franklin Institute. Franklin Medal
  - The Franklin Institute. Honorary Membership
  - The Franklin Institute. Membership
  - John Fritz Medal
  - Harvard College--Diploma
  - Illuminating Engineering Society
  - International Electrical Congress, 1904
  - Institution of Civil Engineers
  - Institution of Electrical Engineers. Faraday Medal
  - Lynn Club of General Electric Engineers
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts. Elector certificate for the, 8 Dec. 1920
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology
  - National Academy of Sciences
  - National Geographic Society, Sep. 1899
  - Night School for Artisans
  - Pan-American Exposition
  - Patent certificate. Electric furnaces, 30 Jan. 1894
  - Patent certificate. Galvanic-battery cell, 14 Oct. 1879
  - Patent certificate. Storage of electricity, 28 Oct. 1879
  - Pi Gamma Mu
  - Royal Institution of Great Britain
  - Smithsonian Institution
  - Sigma Xi, 16 May 1934
  - Tau Beta Pi, 11 Jul. 1934
  - Thomson Electric Welding Co.
    -See Oversized for document
    See Ser.XI for photograph of document
  - Trans-Mississippi & International Exposition, n.d.
  - Tufts College
  - United States. Department of State. Fifth International Congress on Electricity
  - United States. Department of State.
    - Passport issued
  - United States. Department of State., 5 Jul. 1904
    - International Electrical Congress delegate certificate
  - United States. Department of the Navy, n.d.
  - United States Department of the Navy, Mar. 1918
  - United States Universal Exposition at St. Louis. Grand Prize
  - University of Pennsylvania
  - Washington Academy of Sciences, 5 Apr. 1915
  - Yale University
- Series XIII. Clippings and Scrapbooks, 1866-1955; 1 box; 0.5 linear feet
  Individual clippings arranged alphabetically by subject and scrapbooks of collected clippings (#1-4). Clippings have been photocopied onto acid-free Permalife bond paper; copies were filed and original clips were discarded due to brittleness. Topics of clippings include obituaries (of Thomson and colleagues), wedding announcements for Thomson's second marriage, and miscellaneous biographical information on Thomson and his career.
  Scrapbooks primarily contain newspaper clippings, although a small amount of memorabilia and photographs exists within the scrapbooks as well. Some of the clippings in these scrapbooks are duplicates of individual clippings which have been filed by subject. For the most part, the scrapbooks follow a general chronological arrangement. For conservation purposes, these scrapbooks will be microfilmed in the future.
  - Air speed record, n.d. (Box Series XIII-1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1939, n.d.
  - American Welding Society, 1922, n.d.
  - Andrews, William Symes, 1929
  - Astronomy, 1930
  - Benjamin Franklin High School plaque, 1939
  - Biographical. Miscellaneous, 1913-1933, n.d.
  - Boston Museum of Science, 1955
  - Canadian reflecting telescope, 1918
  - Central High School, 1938
  - Clarke, Charles L., 9 Oct. 1941
  - Cold light, n.d.
  - Connor, John J., 1908
  - Crompton, Rookes Evelyn Bell, 1912
  - de Laval steam turbine, 1903
  - Divers. Air mixtures for, n.d.
  - Early dynamo tests, 20 Apr. 1928
  - Eightieth birthday, 1933
  - Einstein's new field theory, 1929
  - Electricity, 1941-1921
  - Electricity at high pressures, 8 Apr. 1899
  - Faraday Centenary, 1931
  - Feronic, 1921
  - Franklin, William S., 1905
  - Franklin Institute, 1929, n.d.
  - Hunter, Rudolph Melville, 1905
  - Illness, 1930, 1934
  - International Electrochemical Commission, 1908
  - Jenks, William Johnson, 1918
  - Lightning, 1908-1909
  - Lindbergh, Charles, 1930
  - Lynn Hospital, n.d.
  - Manipulation of refractory material, 1905
  - Mirror (double reverse image), 1931
  - Nitroglycerine, n.d.
  - Obituaries and memorials, 1937-1940, n.d.
  - Optical glass, n.d.
  - Peek, Frank William, Jr., n.d.
  - Quartz mirrors, 1928
  - Radio, 1922, n.d.
  - Radio waves, n.d.
  - Recording sound patent, [1924]
  - Rice, Edwin Wilbur, 1924
  - Scrapbook #1--Clippings, memorabilia, ca. 1866-1916
  - Scrapbook #2--Clippings
  - Scrapbook #3--Photographs, clippings
  - Scrapbook #4--Death of Elihu Thomson, ca. 1937
  - Seventy-fifth birthday, [1928]
  - Steinmetz, Charles Proteus, 1929
  - Stratton, Samuel Wesley, 1931, n.d.
  - Telescope, n.d.
  - Thomson Club, n.d.
  - Thomson Museum, n.d.
  - Thomson Quarter Century Club, n.d.
  - United States Patent Office, 16 Jan. 1891
  - Ursinus College, n.d.
  - Vibrations, 192-
  - Wedding announcements, 1923
  - Weeks, Edwin R., 1938
  - Welding, 1936
  - Whitney, Willis R., 1929
  - Williams, Francis H., 1936
  - X-rays, 1935
- Series XIV. Memorabilia, 1853-1946; 1 boxes; 0.5 linear feet
  Miscellaneous items collected by Thomson, his wife, and the original organizers of this collection at the APS. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject or name of item. Several pieces of interest in this series date from Thomson's youth, including his birth certificate (1853) and his Philadelphia Central High School commencement program (1870).
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers--Programs, 1917-1932 (Box Series XIV-1)
  - Birth certificate of Elihu Thomson, 5 Apr. 1853
  - British Association for the Advancement of Science. Ticket, 1897
  - Cartoon [re: E.T. inventions], n.d.
  - Cartoons of outings and past events of the G.E. Co. employees, 24 Jun. 1916
  - Central High School Commencement--Program, 10 Feb. 1870
  - Central High School thirtieth anniversary--Program, 23 Jan. 1911
  - "Electrical connections for D.C. current"--Blueprint
  - Electrical machines and electrical appliances--Advertisement, ca. 1873-1874
  - Engineers' meeting--Program, Jun. 1911
  - Frolics in nature--Advertisement
  - Glass fragments, n.d.
  - Hovey, Clara May. Birth certificate, 18 Mar. 1935
  - International Association of Electrical Inspectors--Program, 1933
  - International Congress of Mathematicians--Program, 1932
  - Loomis, E. Tables of logarithms of numbers..., 1848
  - Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin. Memorial exercises in honor of--Program, 16 Apr. 1925
  - National Academy of Sciences--Program, Apr. 1933
  - Passport, 21 Feb. 1927
  - Passport, 7 Feb. 1929
  - Philadelphia Roentgen Ray Society--Program, Jan. 1933
  - [Poem on Elihu Thomson], n.d.
  - The Social Education Congress--Program, 1906
  - Spain, 1911
  - Swampscott Souvenir Directory, 1946
  - Tables in arithmetic. Card of, ca. 1860
  - [Thomson, Elihu.] A collection of variation over many years, n.d.
    misspellings of name
  - Thomson Research Laboratory. [Tribute to E.T. on his wedding], Jan. 1923
  - Visa, 14 Apr. 1923
  - Wire, 25 Jan. 1893
  - [Woodcut print of functional electric machine. E.T.], ca. 1873-1874
- Series XV. Provenencial date, ca. 1937-1943; 2 boxes; 1 linear foot
  Comprised of two subseries. Subseries A contains correspondence generated during the APS Library's attempt to collect Thomson letters from his colleagues after his death. It was the intention of those involved to create the most complete collection of Thomson papers possible; this meant writing to a great many prominent scientists and engineers across the country, asking them to donate any Thomson letters they may have received from him during his lifetime. Major correspondents of this series include Gertrude D. Hess, Assistant Librarian of the APS; Clarissa Hovey Thomson, widow; Roland S. Morris, APS President; Owen D. Young, Chairman of the Board of the General Electric Company; and John A. McManus, Thomson's longtime secretary at General Electric. Correspondence has been placed in five file folders and remain in its original, semi-chronological arrangement.
  Subseries B holds inventories of manuscripts which were produced as the papers were donated. Several of these inventories record the various shipments of papers as they were received from Thomson's widow at their home in Swampscott, Mass. Other inventories were created as the initial processing of the professional correspondence occurred ca. 1937-38.
  Both the correspondence and inventories of Series XV offer a great deal of information on the provenance and initial organization of the Thomson Papers at the APS Library.
  - Correspondence, ca. 1937-1943; 6 Folders (Box Series XV-1)
  - Inventories, ca. 1937-1943; 4 Folders (Box Series XV-2)